I have a confession.
لدي إعتراف.
I have been in an affair
لقد كنت في علاقة غرامية
since I was 17 years old.
منذ سن 17.
I wish I could talk about butterflies in my stomach
أتمنى لو أتحدث عن القلق الذي انتابني
or maps I drew on the ground
أو الخرائط التي رسمتها على الأرض
when I think about this affair,
عند التفكيرفي هذه العلاقة،
but I cannot.
لكنيّ لا أستطيع.
I wish I could talk about sweet words spoken
أتمنى لو أستطيع التحدث عن الكلمات العذبة التى قيلت
or gifts that I received
أو الهدايا التى تلقيتها
from this affair,
في هذه العلاقة،
but I cannot.
لكنيّ لا أستطيع.
All I can tell you about is the aftermath,
كل ما يمكنني أخباركم به هو ما حدث بعد ذلك،
about days I spent constantly asking:
عن الأيام التي قضيتها متسائلة باستمرار:
Why, why, why me?
لما، لما، لما، أنا؟
I remember how it all began.
أتذكر كيف بدأ الأمر كله.
I was in my final year of high school,
لقد كنت في آخر صف لي في المرحلة الثانوية،
and my class had just won in sports,
وقد فاز صفي في الرياضة،
so we were singing and dancing and hugging each other.
لذا كنا نغني ونرقص ونعانق بعضنا البعض.
I went and took a shower.
ثم ذهبت لأستحم
Then I went for dinner.
وذهبت لتناول العشاء.
And when I sat down to eat,
وعندما جلست للأكل،
my teeth started chattering,
بدأت أسناني تصطك،
and so I couldn't put the spoon in my mouth.
ولذا لم أستطع حتى وضع الملعقة في فمي.
I rushed to the nurse's office,
فأسرعت الى مكتب الممرضة،
and because I couldn't talk, I just pointed at my mouth.
ولأني لم أستطع التحدث، أشرت فقط الى فمي.
She didn't know what was happening,
لكنها لم تعلم ما الذي يحدث،
so she told me to lie down,
لذا أخبرتني بأن أستلقي،
and it worked --
ونجح الأمر --
after a few minutes, the chattering stopped.
بعد عدة دقائق، توقف اصطكاك أسناني.
I was about to dash out, and she told me --
كنت على وشك الخروج لكنها أخبرتني --
no, she insisted -- that I go up to the dormitories to sleep.
لا، بل أصرت -- بأن أذهب للسكن الجامعي لأنام.
Here I was in my final year of high school,
حينها كنت في الصف الأخير في المرحلة الثانوية.
just a few months from doing my end of high school exams
بعد أشهر قليلة من إنهائي إمتحانات الثانوية
and a few days from doing a set of exams we call here in Kenya "mocks,"
وأيام قليلة من أداء مجموعة من الإمتحانات نسميها في كينيا (موكس)
which are somehow meant to gauge how prepared one is for the final exams.
والتي تقيس مدى استعداد الطلاب للإمتحانات النهائية.
There is no way I was going to sleep
لذا كان من المستحيل أن أنام
and let a set of exams mock me.
وأترك مجموعة من الإمتحانات تهزأ بي.
I went to class, sat down,
ذهبت للصف ثم جلست
took my Kenyan history notes,
وأخذت ملحوظات التاريخ الكينيّ،
and there I was, down Kenyan coastal town,
وقد كنت هناك، وسط المدينة الكينية الساحلية،
with the great Mekatilili wa Menza,
مع مكاتيلي وا مينزا العظيمة،
the Giriama woman who led her people against British colonial rule.
المرأة الجيريامية التي قادت شعبها ضد الحكم البريطاني الاستعماري.
Then, without any notice,
ثم بدون أي مقدمات،
my left hand started jerking,
بدأت يدي اليسري بالارتعاش،
and it was as if I was marking imaginary papers.
وبدا الأمر وكأنّي أصحح أوراقًا خيالية.
In and out it went,
كان ذلك يجري داخليًا وخارجيًا،
and with every stroke, one by one,
ومع كل ضربة، واحدة تلو الأخرى،
my classmates stopped concentrating on their reading
توقف زملائي عن التركيز في القراءة
and started looking at me.
وبدأوا​ بالنظر إليّ.
And I tried really hard to stop it,
حاولت بشدة إيقاف يدي،
but I couldn't,
لكنيّ لم أستطع،
because it had a life of its own.
لأن الحياة كانت تدب فيها بشكل منفصل.
And then, when it was sure everybody was looking at us,
وبعدها، عندما تأكدت يدي أن الجميع ينظر الينا،
in its final show and official introduction,
في عرضها الأخير والمقدمة الرسمية،
I had my first full-blown seizure,
كان هذه أول نوبة كاملة تحدث لي،
which was the beginning of what has been a 15-year-long affair.
والتي كانت بداية لهذه العلاقة التي دامت 15عامًا.
Seizures are the trademark characteristic for most types of epilepsy,
النوبات هى الصفة المميزة لأغلب أنواع الصرع،
and every first-ever seizure needs to be assessed by a doctor
وتحتاج أول نوبة طبيباً لفحصها
to determine if one has epilepsy
ليقرر إذا ما كان الشخص مصاباً بالصرع
or if it's a symptom of something else.
أو أنها أعراض شيء أخر.
In my case, it was confirmed that I had epilepsy.
في حالتي، جزم أنيّ مصابة بالصرع.
I spent a large chunk of my time in hospital and at home,
قضيت وقتاً طويلاً في المستشفى والمنزل،
and only went back to do my final exams.
وعدت فقط لأداء إمتحاناتي النهائية.
I had seizures in between papers,
أصبت بنوبات أثناء الإمتحانات،
but managed to get good enough grades
لكن تمكنت من الحصول على درجات جيدة كفايةً
to be admitted for an actuarial science degree
للإلتحاق بدرجة في علم حسابات التأمين
at the University of Nairobi.
في جامعة نيروبي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Unfortunately, I had to drop out in my second year.
لسوء الحظ، تركت الدراسة في السنة الثانية
I didn't have good enough coping skills
لم تكن لدي مهارات تأقلم كافية
and a support community around me.
ومحيط داعم من حوليّ.
I was lucky enough to get a job,
كنت محظوظة ما يكفي لأحصل على وظيفة،
but I was fired from that job when I had a seizure in the workplace.
لكني طردت منها عندما أصبت بنوبة في مكان العمل.
So I found myself in a space
لذا وجدت نفسي في فضاء تامٍ
where I was constantly asking myself
حيث دائمًا ما كنت أسال نفسي
why this had to happen to me.
لما يحدث هذا لي.
I lived in denial for a long time,
لقد عشت في نكران للذات لمدة طويلة،
and the denial was maybe because of the things that had happened,
وقد يكون النكران بسب الأشياء التى حدثت.
dropping out of school and being fired from my job.
ترك الدراسة والطرد من العمل.
Or maybe it was because of the things I had heard about epilepsy
وقد يكون بسب الأشياء التى سمعتها عن الصرع
and about people living with epilepsy:
وعن المصاببن به:
that they would never live on their own;
وأنهم لا يعيشون بمفردهم أبدًا:
that they would never travel on their own
ولا يسافرون وحدهم مطلقًا
or even get work;
أو حتي يحصلون على عمل؛
that they were outcasts,
أنهم منبوذين
with a spirit in them that they needed to be delivered from.
وتتلبسهم روح هم بحاجة للتخلص منها.
And so the more I thought about these things,
ولذا كلما فكرت في هذه الأشياء،
the more my seizures became,
كلما ازدات النوبات،
and I spent days with my legs locked,
وقضيت أيام ورجلي مربوطة،
my speech became blurred
وأصبح كلامي غير واضحاً
and on days on end, this is how I'd be.
وعندما انتهت تلك الأيام، هذا ما أصبحت عليه.
Two or three days after a seizure,
بعد يومين أو ثلاثة بعد النوبة،
my head and my hand would still be twitching.
ظل رأسي ويدي يرتعشان.
I felt lost,
أحسست بالضياع،
like I'd lost everything,
وكأنما فقدت كل شيء،
and sometimes,
وفي بعض الأحيان،
even the will to live.
حتى الرغبة في الحياة.
(Sigh)
(تنهيدة)
I had so much frustration in me.
كان بداخلي إحباط كبير.
And so I started writing,
ولذا بدأت بالكتابة،
because the people around me didn't have answers
لأن الناس من حولي لم يكن لديهم إجابات
to the questions that I had.
لأسئلتي.
And so I wrote my fears
ولهذا كتبت مخاوفي
and my doubts.
وشكوكي
I wrote about my good days and my bad days and my really ugly days,
كتبت عن أيامي الحسنة والسيئة وأيامي البغيضة جدًا
and I shared them on a blog.
وشاركت هذا في مدونة.
And before long,
وقبلها بكثير،
I began to be seen and heard by people who had epilepsy
بدأ أُناس مصابون بالصرع يروني ويسمعونني
and their families,
وأسرهم،
and even those who did not have the diagnosis.
وحتى أولئك غير المشخصين به.
And I moved from that girl who constantly asked why me
وتغيرت من الفتاة التي تتسأل دائمًا لما أنا
to one who not only self-advocates,
إلى تلك التي لم تكن فقط داعمة لنفسها
but does it for those who are yet to find their voices.
بل أيضًا تقوم بذلك لأولئك الذين لم يجدوا أصواتهم بعد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
My seizures are greatly reduced, from two to three times a day,
قلت نوباتي بشكل كبير حتى اثنين أو ثلاثة في اليوم،
to sometimes two to three times in one year.
في بعض الأحيان اثنين إلى ثلاثة في السنة.
I went on --
وتابعت --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I went on to employ five people,
تابعت تعيين خمسة أشخاص،
when I began what was Kenya's first
عندما افتتحت ما يعتبر في كينيا أول
free mental health and epilepsy support line.
مستشفى للصحة النفسية المجانية ودعم الصرع.
And I travel --
وسافرت --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I travel to speak about my affair,
وأسافر للتحدث عن مشكلتي،
all these things that I had been told
وكل الأشياء التي عرفت
people like me living with epilepsy could never be able to do.
بأن أناس مثلي يعيشون مع الصرع لا يستطيعون فعلها.
Every year, a population as big as 80 percent of Nairobi
كل عام، نسبة بقدر 80% من سكان نيروبي
gets diagnosed with epilepsy
يتم تشخيصهم بالصرع
across the globe.
حول العالم.
And they, like me,
وهم، مثلي،
go through the emotions of stigma and exclusion.
يشعرون بالعار والنفي.
And so I have made it my life journey
ولذا جعلتها رحلتي في الحياة
to keep these conversations going,
لإبقاء هذه المحادثات جارية،
and I keep confessing about my affair
ولأظل أعترف بصراعي
so that those people who do not have the diagnosis
حتى أولئك الناس غير المشخصين به
might know and might have a constant reminder
ربما يعرفون ويكون لديهم تذكار دائم
that it is alright to engage with people like us,
بأنه لا بأس من التعامل معنا،
that as long as they pull down the walls of stigma and exclusion,
وأنهم لطالما يهدمون حوائط العار والنفي،
that we, just like them,
وأننا، مثلهم تمامًا،
can be able to take anything life throws at us.
بإمكاننا أخذ أي شيء ترمي به الحياة إلينا.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)